Hello everyone. Visceral
techniques including ganglia
release, liver and splenic
pumps, mesenteric lifts,
colonic simulation.
My name is Sammy
Giorgio. I am one of your
academic medicine
scholars giving you this
lecture today, and I
would like to thank
Dr. Theodore Flom for
allowing me to do so.
At the conclusion of this
session slash course,
the students should be
able to apply palpation or
assessment to areas of
congestion or restriction
before and after omt
understand the principles of
performing visceral treatment
describe the anatomical
components of the mesentery
and its supportive
and nutritive functions
to the abdominal organs
compare and contrast
relative and absolute
contraindications and perform
the following techniques
ganglia release liver
pump splenic pump
mesenteric abdominal lips
and colonic simulation
So as this is a lab prep
lecture and per the guidance
of Dr. Flown, we're just
going to work together through
the lab handout, and I'm
just going to be reading
off the slides, which are
pulled directly from your
handout. So if you want to
follow along, please do so.
Just to start, we're
going to go over
the principles of
visceral treatment.
So visceral manipulation
treats palpable motion
dysfunction of viscera to improve
their physiologic function.
This is consistent with
the osteopathic theory
that states that improved
motion leads to improved
function. In addition,
visceral manipulation applies
osteopathic philosophy,
principles, and practices to
visceral dysfunction. This
involves addressing related
components of the
musculoskeletal, neurologic,
respiratory, and circulatory
systems. For a visceral problem
resulting from somatovisceral
reflex, the somatic
structure responsible is
treated. If a visceral or
somatic problem is caused
by a viscerosomatic reflex,
the viscera are
treated. In the case of
viscero-visceral reflex
causing a visceral
problem, both involved
viscera are treated.
In visceral dysfunction,
applying a force that
is exactly matched in
force, direction, and
speed as the dysfunctional
strain will result in
tissue changes and its return
to a more physiological
normal dispensability.
In the process,
there is a dissipation of
heat, movement of fluid,
and a restructuring of
the elasticity curve.
The goal of treatment
is achieving a state of
balanced ligamentous
tension, normal motion
with respiration,
balanced inherent motion,
and normalization of
the nervous system along
with fluid, nutrition,
and pressure exchange.
The first technique we begin
with is the ganglia release
technique. The celiac and
superior mesenteric and
inferior mesenteric ganglia
may be treated by the same
method altering the hand
position on the abdomen for
the different ganglia. The
celiac area is below the
xiphoid, the inferior mesenteric
just above the umbilicus,
and the superior mesenteric
halfway between the two.
This technique is
contraindicated in patients
with a post-operative
midline abdominal scar.
To perform this technique,
the patient is laying
supine with the physician
standing at the side
of the patient. The
physician's finger pads of one
or both hands are lined
up along the patient's
mid-abdominal line
contacting the skin just over
the collateral ganglion
that is to be inhibited
the physician applies a
gentle downward pressure
until the resistance of
the underlying tissues
is felt and its resistance
is matched this pressure
is held until a softening
or release is felt
here we can see the
ganglia release technique
being performed these
images are provided in your
handout as well on the
left image you can see
the physician is performing
it over the celiac
ganglia. In the middle
image, it is over the
superior mesenteric ganglia,
and on the right image,
it is over the inferior
mesenteric ganglia.
The next technique we will be
going over is the
abdominal lifts.
Abdominal lifts are a safe,
simple means of addressing
ptosis and congestion
of the abdominal viscera
and its mesenteries. To
perform this technique, we
will first have the patient
laying supine with their
knees bent to 90 degrees
and their feet flat on the
table. The physician then
stands at the side of the
patient that is to be treated.
The physician contacts
the lower left quadrant
of the abdomen just
superior to the inguinal
ligament and gently inserts the
finger pads into the patient's
abdomen. The physician
then gently lifts the
patient's abdominal contents
obliquely towards the
right upper quadrant until
slight tension is palpable.
The tissues are held
in this position until a
release is felt. The contents
can then be moved slightly
further towards the
patient's right upper quadrant.
The position should be
attentive so that the lift
occurs to the internal
organs and not just to the
anterior abdominal wall.
Steps 3 and 4 are repeated
until the patient's
maximal release has
been accomplished.
And for the right lower
quadrant, repeat steps 1 to
5 lifting vertically toward
the right upper quadrant.
These images provided are
directly from your handout
and demonstrate the
abdominal lift techniques
we just discussed. On
the left, you can see the
physician's finger pads
contacting just superior to
the inguinal ligament on
the patient's lower left
quadrant as he prepares
to direct his vector of
force obliquely towards
the patient's right upper
quadrant versus the image
on your right demonstrates
the physician palpating
the patient's lower right
quadrant as he prepares
his vector of force
superiorly towards the
patient's right upper quadrant.
We're going to move on
to our next technique,
which is colonic stimulation,
which is contraindicated
in the settings of
bowel obstructions,
abdominal neoplasms, and
undiagnosed abdominal pain.
The technique is performed
by having the patient lie
supine with the physician
standing at the patient's
side. The physician places
the pads of their fingers
on the abdominal wall
overlying the splenic flexure
of the colon. The physician
rolls the finger pads
along the bowel in the
direction of colonic flow.
The physician releases
pressure and repositions the
hands one hand's width
further along the colon
toward the sigmoid region.
After several excursions down
the descending colon, the
position repositions the
hand to begin at the hepatic
flexure working along
the transverse and descending
colon. After several
of these excursions, the
position repositions the
hand to begin at the region
of the cecum working along
the ascending, transverse,
and descending colon.
These images below demonstrate
the colonic stimulation
technique and are also
included in your handout.
The image on the left
demonstrates the beginning
of the technique where the
physician places the pad
of their fingers on the
abdominal wall overlying
the splenic flexure of the
colon before rolling their
fingers along the bowel
in the direction of
colonic flow. The middle
image then demonstrates when
the physician has positioned
his or her hands along
the hepatic flexure and again
work along the transverse
and descending colon
before the final image
on the right demonstrates
the physician repositioning
their hands to begin at
the cecum and working along
the ascending transverse
and descending colons.
The next technique is the
liver pump which is performed
by having the patient lies
supine and the physician
sitting at the right
side of the patient. The
physician's left hand is
placed under the ribcage at the
level of the liver while
the right hand is laid over
the lower costal cartilages
overlaying the liver.
They gently compress
and palpate the liver
with both hands. The
physician's hands then
exert pressure directly
toward the center of
the patient's body
springing the ribs inward.
A springing motion is
carried out at two per second
and continued for 30
seconds to several minutes.
These images below show
the liver pump technique
with the image on the left
demonstrating how the left
hand of the physician is
under the rib cage at the
level of the liver while
the right hand is overlaying
the costal cartilage is
overlaying the liver.
And the image on the right
is demonstrating how you
may apply a gentle compressive
force between those
two to palpate the liver.
The next step of this
technique would then to be
the exerting the springing
pressure directly towards
the center of the patient's
body, which would be carried
out at two per second
and continued for 30
seconds to several minutes.
The final technique we
will be discussing is the
splenic pump, which has
contraindications including
infectious mononucleosis,
any splenic enlargement,
and any neoplasms
infiltrating the spleen.
The technique is performed
by having the patient lie
supine with the physician
standing on the left side of
the patient. The physician's
right hand abducts the
patient's left arm 90 degrees
and exerts gentle traction.
The physician places their
left hand on the lower
costal cartilages overlaying
the spleen, with the
fingers following the intercostal
spaces. The physician's
left hand then exerts
pressure directly towards the
center of the patient's
body, springing the ribs
inward. A springing motion
is carried out for two per
second and continued at 30
seconds to several minutes.
These images below are
demonstrating the splenic
pump. The image on the left
is demonstrating how the
physician's right hand
abducts the patient's left
arm 90 degrees and exerts
gentle traction, while
the image on the right is
demonstrating the left hand
which is overlaying over
the lower costal cartilages
which are overlying
spleen with the fingers
following the intercostal
spaces, and that left hand
exerts a pressure directly
towards the center of the
patient's body, which
springs the ribs inward.
This springing motion is
carried out at two per second
and continued for 30
seconds to several minutes.
So that concludes the
lab prep lecture for this
lab and all the material
related with it. I
just wanted to say thank
you again for all of
your time and attention,
and I would like to just
thank Dr. Flaum again
for allowing me to give
this lecture to you all.
Have a wonderful day.
And if you have time,
please take a moment to fill
out the lab feedback
form at your convenience.
I know we all greatly
appreciate it. Thank you.